Researchers have identified criticality
emerging within brain organoids, these
are lab-grown human brain friends.
Now they are often used for research and
there's also a few data centers that
have been set up using brain organoids
and they're thought to be a potential
alternative to artificial intelligence.
Now, this is a preprint although that is
not a reason to disbelieve it. There is
also supporting evidence for this in the
literature.
Also, just because a lot of people do
not know this, if you're not publishing
in science, preprints do not mean bad.
It just means that they have not yet
been fully peer-reviewed and published.
If you're curious about a preprint,
check out the journal in which it's
being reviewed by and also check out the
lab and see if they are reputable.
Criticality is a theoretical point
between order and chaos and it is
thought to be necessary for
consciousness. Consciousness as we know
it as being awake and aware. It's
thought to be interfered with when you
go under anesthesia. There is still a
great deal that we do not understand
about consciousness and this is not to
say that brain organoids are definitely
conscious. It means that they share
qualities that we have in our own brains
and that makes sense. They are lab-grown
miniature versions of our brains and
they have demonstrated the capacity for
learning and memory.
You can train them using ordered or
disordered signals and some researchers
have claimed sentience which is still
controversial partially because we have
no measure for sentience or
consciousness at all. I mean, you could
toss the mirror test at them. I mean,
some of them have eyes. However, the
mirror test is really not a measure of
consciousness. I mean, it could be but
fish pass it. That might mean that fish
are conscious or that consciousness is
just something we fundamentally do not
understand and probably won't because we
are operating in philosophy when we
can't really measure an outcome. So what
is preventing us from making a brain
that is comparable to a human brain and
would that be conscious?
Well, we do already know that they have
brain waves, largely delta and those are
associated with an unconscious state
although they do have other brain waves.
They match the same brain wave patterns
as a preterm baby, although they are
significantly smaller, usually a few
millimeters across. Although, some
researchers are trying to make them
bigger and more complex because you can
lob them together as an assembloid.
Or you can grow them as generally
larger, and many researchers are trying
to do that to make the perfect model for
a brain. And that is largely what is
going on in the research side of things
where people do things like medical
research and trying to understand the
brain. And then there's the computation
side where things have largely gone
two-dimensional to solve the size
problem.
Yeah, the bigger they get, the more
likely they are to become hypoxic. And
yes, you can give them a primitive
version of a circulatory system by
lobbing them together with other
organoids.
You can give them a little mini heart
and a little mini circulatory system if
you would really like to. And you can
also create little mini bodies, which I
affectionately call homunculi.
These can include a sensory system like
eyes and a spinal cord and physical
sensation. When we talk about them in
robots like spider bots, and there are
others, for the most part they're
translating stimuli, so what they're
experiencing around them into electrical
impulses that have meaning, but they're
not experiencing sensation in the same
way that we do. In order to do that,
they're going to need a spinal cord
organoid. And it does get a little bit
morbid because the thought around
building these little homunculi is that
they can be twins for patients. So, if
you aren't sure how someone is going to
respond to a treatment, well, you can
grow them a version of them, and
physiologically it should respond as the
patient will.
Now, a question you might ask is, why
robots? Why are these being combined
with robots if largely the divide
between using them as AI and using them
for medical research? Why is anyone
embodying them?
Well, yeah, there is another unhinged
side of this equation, and I don't
really know which it belongs to because
many of the people involved in creating
organoid robotics are also in medical
research.
I mean, spider bot was the first and it
is still near and dear to my heart and
metabot seems to not be a thing.
That paper came out a few years ago and
it was kind of just a vague idea for how
to make a brain organoid robot. It never
came to fruition. But there is real
organoid robots out there. I think one
of the interesting applications for
these is honestly prosthetics. I mean,
they can interface between electronics
and, you know, squishy biological stuff.
You can borrow from nature or rather
steal from nature. You can grow
organoids and use that as a sensory
interface for a robot. It can
communicate with carbon. Graphene is a
great use of it.
In this way, you can give a robot a
sensory experience even if we don't
consider it an experience in the way
that we do.
Will that necessarily be brain organoids
that are doing the interfacing or skin
or nerves? Maybe. Maybe all of the
above. I imagine that you could have
nerve organoids that integrate with the
electronics and then that can integrate
into the actual nervous system. And
yeah, brain computer interfaces are also
another really good use of these guys.
Your body is kind of irreplaceable. So
if we can grow a version of your body
that can connect with it and do minimal
invasiveness, then that seems like a win
for everyone.
Now I do want to reiterate that just
because we may see some signs of brain
activity that are similar to brain
activity necessary for consciousness,
that doesn't mean that they're
necessarily having an experience. Not in
the way that we are and we do have to
think about scale.
Although, some researchers at John
Hopkins want to make them 1 cm at least
with their new circulatory systems.
Just to get an idea of what 1 cm means,
that's the same as a mouse's brain and
they are capable of some pretty serious
cognition.
So I think we are at the point where we
should be genuinely concerned about what
this could end up being and what kind of
undue suffering it might cause. How can
we address this? Honestly, I have no
idea. I think there's a whole lot of
good that could come out of it, and yes,
there are ethical concerns. I'm just
glad that I'm not responsible for making
these decisions.
Either way, I will keep you up-to-date,
and I hope you've enjoyed this. Follow
for more.
>> I can see the tiny prokaryotes swarming
in the culture.